[Music]
This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
All right. So for those people who are
watching on uh on Saturday night live or
wherever this thing is being broadcast,
if you have questions that you want to
communicate with me about or you want to
post some interesting insight or I'm
speaking about a physics insight, if you
want to put up a interesting problem
that you may have either seen or heard
of or
uh had a professor 40 years ago give you
to solve and you've never been able to
solve it since
or um well that sort of thing
then rather than send it to me by email
and expect me to send it out to
everybody I thought we could put these
things up on
a site which I created which thus far
I've got exactly one question on
Suskin's blog physics for everyone
that's one word.blogpot.com.
Use it. Don't abuse it.
No. Uh,
no. Um, pmics, please. I do not answer
pmical questions.
I've learned not to. It's taken me some
time. And uh, and pmical things will be
immediately eliminated.
serious physics questions. Uh even if
they're very simple, they do not have to
be
either deep, profound, difficult, or
just some simple insights about some of
the material, that'll be fine. Questions
about physics, even outside the scope of
the class, are fine.
No questions about whether
string theory is even wrong.
Anyway, let's uh let's begin tonight's
lecture. I put this up on the top for
I tried to get to it. Could did anyone
else have a problem?
I don't know. I don't have any problem
getting to it, but uh
uh it may be that the it may be that
people are having pro problems getting
to it. Um, if you do have problem, send
me an email and I'll see. I I'm a
complete incompetent at this. I just uh
tried to do it. It seemed to be
successful. I seem to be able to get to
it. I put an announcement on it. Um,
maybe
more than one thread on there. I was
just trying to
I don't know. I don't even know what a
thread is.
Was the question that you got recent?
No. Came the first day. Well, recent.
Fairly recent. Yeah.
Anyway, uh let's keep going. If you try
to use it and it doesn't work, let me
know.
You have to sign in. I think
or something. Yeah,
I don't know.
I'll try to find out. I'll try to uh get
somebody who knows about these things.
Okay.
Let's um talk about the invariance of
the laws of nature
under various kinds of operations. Of
course, what I really have in mind is of
course Lorent transformations.
The fact that the laws of nature do not
change when we make a Lorent
transformation.
But let's talk about the strategy for
cooking up laws which look the same in
every reference frame.
Uh the strategy is to express those laws
in a form
um which really doesn't
depend on any particular choice of
coordinates
to express the laws in some physical way
that as I said that doesn't depend on
specific coordinates and then choose a
set of coordinates and rewrite what
you've expressed in a language
appropriate to those coordinates. An
example,
uh, the shortest distance between two
points. The definition of a straight
line is the shortest distance between
two points. The shortest trajectory
between two points.
You can
figure out what a straight line is
connecting a pair of points by sticking
a thumbtack.
Don't, please don't stick thumbtacks in
the uh
in the black boards and the white
boards, but you could stick a couple of
thumbtacks in, take a string, pull it as
tight as you can,
and that will guarantee that you found
the shortest distance between those two
points and that you will call a straight
line. In other words, the law for a
straight line, this is not actually a
law of physics. Now there's a definition
of a straight line but it's been defined
in a way that made no reference to um uh
to any particular coordinates. An
example of a law of physics that's
closely related to this is that the path
of a light ray between two points is a
straight line. That's a law. And now
could be stated that the path of a light
ray between two points is the shortest
distance between those two points.
That's a light ray in a vacuum.
A generalization of that for light
moving through various kinds of
materials is that the time that it takes
a light ray to go from one point to
another is the shortest possible
uh time. All right. So those and notice
again I did not use any definition of
spatial coordinates in expressing those
laws. Those laws were expressed in a
coordinate independent way.
But then I can then use coordinates to
build myself up in mathematics and to
solve some equations involving those
laws. Let me give you an example. Just
exactly this law here that light travels
along the shortest path or just a
problem of finding the shortest path
between two points. All right. Once I
know that the shortest path that that's
what I'm looking for is the shortest
path. I take some coordinates
X and Y.
I label the two points of interest. I
give them coordinates X1 Y1 X2 Y2. I
won't bother right now.
And then I write down
well first of all I imagine a curve
connecting them.
I imagine a curve. In fact, I'm going to
imagine all possible curves connecting
them. And I break up that curve into
little segments.
Each little segment can be characterized
by a differential, meaning a small
displacement dx and dy.
So let's take a little displacement over
here and label it dx and dy.
Eventually, of course, we're going to go
to the limit where we chop it up into
smaller and smaller pieces and do some
calculus, but for the moment, just call
them dx and dy.
And now, let's write the length of the
curve. The length of the curve is just
the summation over all of these little
differential elements of the length of
each differential element. The length of
each differential element, we can write
ds, s for length. I'm not sure why I use
s for length except it's traditional to
do so. And that's equal to the square
root of dx^2 + d y^2.
That's of course the Pythagorean
theorem.
It does not depend on what the
orientation of the axes are with any
orientation for the axes. As long
incidentally, as I as long as I use the
same units for X and Y, I would get a
rather bizarre expression as I've
emphasized several times if I used
meters for X and uh and feet for Y. But
as long as I use the same units, it
doesn't matter which way I orient the um
the axes on the blackboard, the
expression for the length of a little
differential element is still the same.
And now I add them all up. I add them up
by integrating
s
for the total length becomes the
integral which is just the sum of all
these little differential elements here
square root of dx^2 + d y^2. Now that's
a strange for some of you that may be a
bit of a strange looking expression. A
square root of dx^2 + d y^2. It's not
really that strange. You could think of
y, you could think of x as the
independent variable and then rewrite
this in another form
integral.
Let's take out a factor of dx.
And now in the square root, since I've
taken out a factor of dx,
that means I should divide what's in the
square root by dx^2. And that just
becomes 1 + dy by dx^2.
d y by dx^2. That's just a derivative of
the dependent variable y with respect to
x. And this is a perfectly good integral
if you know what y of x is.
That's the length between the two
points. And now you can set yourself to
task. Let me find the curve which gives
the smallest value for this that
connects two points.
This of course is very similar to the
principle of least action which says
that the trajectory of a particle in
spacetime
sweeps out a path of least action.
Again action being some kind of integral
of a lrangeian.
Very similar kind of thing. The main
point here is that we've expressed the
original law
without coordinates and therefore we can
be sure that when we introduce
coordinates the answer will not depend
on our choice of coordinates. Yes sir.
Can you define distance without
coordinate?
Uh
sure. Tape measure.
Of course, the tape measure has
coordinates along it, but at this but uh
the point is it doesn't matter how you
reorient the axes, the tape measure will
always give the same expression. So it
was it was defined by the string or the
tape measure connecting the two points
but without regard to how I chose the xy
axis. But then in an attempt to actually
mathematically implement the
mathematical problem, I introduced a set
of coordinates to express the problem in
a mathematical form. And so yes, I think
the problem is expressed without uh
without uh uh coordinates. It's a good
question, but for the moment I'll I'll
leave it uh hang as
uh in the way that I said it. Okay. Now,
so that's an example. Now, what went
into that example? The most important
thing that went into that example
mathematically was Pythagoras's theorem
that the distance between two points is
the square root of the sum of the
squares. And that does not the sum of
the squares of the coordinates. And it
has exactly the same form if you were to
tilt the axes.
that in itself is an expression of
invariance
that the distance between two
neighboring points is invariant. Meaning
to say it doesn't depend on your
coordinates.
And of course we're familiar with this.
We've gone through it several times.
dx^2
plus d y^2
doesn't depend on your choice of
coordinates. And the way to check that
it's exactly the sorts of things we've
checked up till now is we've taken a
coordinate system rotated the coordinate
system x y x prime yp prime
theta an angle between them and we've
discovered that the that the law of
transformation the mathematical law of
rotation of coordinates
is the law which keeps
x^2 + y^2 fixed dx^2 + d y^2 fixed and
the sums of squares of the components of
any vector.
In fact, any quantity which transforms
the same way as x and y as the
coordinate as the components of the
position vector the sums of squares will
be invariant.
So that's the strategy. The strategy is
to find ways
to find basically all the ways of
constructing quantities which are
invariant under the operation that
you're interested in
and then express the laws of physics
perhaps in terms of action principles.
Action principles are very efficient
ways of expressing laws of nature in a
way that doesn't depend on coordinates.
You just say the length is minimum
or the time for for a light ray to go
from one place to another is minimum or
the action is minimum. All right? But
you must check that the expression that
you've written down for the action
really doesn't depend on your choice of
coordinates. And so it becomes a
exercise in figuring out how to form
invariance.
Invariance means things which don't
change when you change the coordinates
in particular way. Did you have a
question?
Yeah question. Is this dependent on the
underlying geometry?
Yes. This this is dependent on the fact
that the underlying geometry was
uklitian geometry. And that's a good
point.
uh there's a generalization of it of
course the idea of geodessic in a curved
space but I'm trying now to be as simple
as possible and give you the simplest
examples
when you say transformed in the same way
uh as x and y you mean the cosiness
yes yes yes exactly supposing I have any
pair of quantities let's call them ax
and a y now of course secretly what I
have in mind is the components of
vectors but let's just call them ax and
a y and um I assume that they transform
which means that when you look at them
from different coordinate that first of
all the components themselves depend on
your choice of of coordinates and let's
just assume that they transform in the
form ax prime is equal to ax cossine
theta I think it's minus a y
sin theta
And likewise for a y prime
= ax
sin theta
plus I guess a y cosine theta. This is
the same way that x and y themselves
would transform
this law of transformation from one
coordinate system to another defines
what we call a vector. Now, of course,
let's go. We can also introduce a
z-axis.
Uh, and we should introduce a z-axis.
I'm just too lazy to write down the more
complicated transformation law. And it
is more complicated when you can rotate
around in three dimensions. But this is
the idea. And once you have established
that the quantities that you have are
components of a vector, it follows
immediately that the sums of the squares
of them ax^2 + a y 2
is invariant. What that means is that if
you make such a transformation
then this will be equal to ax prime^ 2 +
a y prime squared.
All right. So establishing that a pair
of components transforms as a vector
allows you not only to transform them
but to write down expressions which
don't change when you change your
coordinates. the sums of squares of
components of a vector are sort of the
leading uh candidate for that kind of
thing.
Okay, so that's uh and dx2 + d y^2 is a
special example.
Let's talk about
um
yeah
now we know the analog of this for the
special theory of relativity. We've gone
through it a couple of times. Basically
the same rules except instead of having
two spatial components we have a space
and a time component. Let's call it t.
And then same kind of transformations
except instead of cosine and s of theta
we have hyperbolic angles.
In the same way we would say that
anything that transforms the same way as
x y z and t incidentally did we ever
talk about how y and z transform?
No. Well let's do let's fill that gap in
right now. It's exceedingly simple.
Let's let's fill that gap. We
found the transformation law x prime is
equal to x * k omega
minus
uh t not the
not y t cinch omega
t prime is equal to x - x cinch omega
plus t cos omega.
Now this is for a lorren transformation
where the relative velocity between the
two frames is along the xaxis.
If we wanted to have the relative
velocity along some other axis, we'd
have to do something more complicated.
But this is for where the two frames of
reference are moving relative to each
other right along the x-axis. What about
the Y and Z components of vectors? Well,
the Y and Z components of vectors simply
don't change. When you boost, boost is
another word for doing a Lorent
transformation along a given axis. When
you do a Lorent transformation along the
X-axis, the Y and Z components don't
change.
A meter stick
oriented perpendicular to its own
velocity does not get Lorent
transformed.
uh the arguments for that can be found
in the internet uh lectures on the
special theory of relativity two or
three quarters ago and I'm not going to
go through them now other than to just
say that the rest of the transformation
law is y prime is equal to y and z prime
is equal to z
now of course lent transformations are
not the only things we can do that will
keep our description of physics fixed.
We can also rotate coordinates. We could
rotate among x, y, and z. Those are
spatial rotations. When you combine
together spatial rotations with Lorent
transformations along a given axis, if
you then rotate your coordinates,
rotate your coordinates, you can then
use the rotation of coordinates to boost
along a different axis. That's a
complicated combination of different
kinds of transformations.
uh the question is what are the
quantities which are invariant when we
have all four components here.
Okay. Now the the combination which is
invariant is more or less obvious. It's
just not just t ^2 - x^2
t ^2 - x^2 that was proper time. That
was the thing which was invariant under
a boost along the x axis. If you
transform along the x-axis with a
standard Lorent transformation
but supposing
I do a different transformation instead
of doing a lent transformation I just do
a rotation of coordinates
rotation of x into y for example. Well
if I just rotate my spatial coordinates
and do nothing to time. In other words,
this is just an ordinary rotation of
spatial coordinates doing absolutely
nothing to time. No velocity involved,
just a change of orientation.
Then time doesn't change. Time doesn't
change if all you do is transform the
orientation of your space coordinates.
But x, y, and z transform into each
other. So t ^2 minus x^2 cannot possibly
be invariant. In fact, when you do a
rotation, the quantity which is
invariant is x^2 + y^2 + z ^2.
That suggests that the invariant is t ^2
- x^2 - y^2 - z ^2.
And that's correct. Under a lorren
transformation,
this lorren transformation here, t ^2 -
x^2 does not change. That we've already
established, right? Furthermore, since y
and z don't change, t ^2 - x^2 - y^2 - z
square doesn't change.
Okay,
so this is the quantity
which lorren transformations and
rotations of space keep invariant
don't change. Okay, we'll come back to
that. We'll come back to that later uh
another time. Oh maybe today.
Now any quantity which transforms under
lent transformations and spatial
rotations in the same way as xyz and t
is called a four vector.
A four vector is just a quantity which
transforms as the basic coordinates
themselves. If you have a four vector,
it has a time component and it has three
space components.
The difference between the square of the
time component and the three space
component squared, that always is an
invariant.
It's the analog of the length of a
vector but in spaceime.
All right? So if we have a general for
vector for example just take instead of
the coordinates themselves
you have a trajectory and you have a
little interval along the trajectory
then you have a four vector which is
just dt
dx dy and dz
and dt ^2 minus dx^2 - dy^ 2 - dz^ 2 is
the thing which is invariant for that
little interval. You could add them up
the same way we added up
length along a curve
and that will define the proper time
along the curve. So it doesn't just have
to be it's not just x and t but xyz and
t. And this is the combination that
forms the invariant proper distance
along a curve along a word line.
It's extremely important to us to know
how to form invariance.
And in order to know how to form
invariance we have to specify how
quantities transform. If we don't know
how things transform, we don't know how
to put them together uh to make
invariance.
All right. So, what kind of objects are
there?
Well, first of all, there are four
vectors. That's not the simplest kind of
thing. There's an even simpler thing
that's even simpler than uh than a four
vector. It's a scalar. A scalar is a
thing which doesn't transform the same
at all. It's the same in every reference
frame.
Uh can you think of anything which is a
scalar? Sometimes called an invariant.
I'm not going to distinguish between
invariance and scalers. Uh for this
class, can you think of anything uh
which is uh uh an
invariant or
I heard it charge
electric charge. Electric charge of a
moving particle is exactly the same as a
stationary particle. Uh, if you at rest
watch my electron moving along, you
you'll ascribe to it exactly the same
electric charge. I was just thinking of
my name. My name is Leonardo.
Okay, my name doesn't change when I
start to move. It's a scalar.
Uh, some other scalers that happen in
physics.
Mass.
Mass is a scalar. Rest mass is a scalar.
Yes, mass is a scalar. But here's here's
another scalar. The well uh dt ^2us dx^2
- d y^2 - dz^ 2. It's a thing which
doesn't change under the wrench
transformation. Now officially you would
call that an invariant. And uh there's
but I'm just going to call it a scalar.
A thing which does not change when you
lurent transform or when you rotate.
That's called an invariant.
If we can build up our laws of nature
out of invariance, then our laws of
nature will be invariant. As simply
stated, if we can build up and express
the laws of nature, we can express them
in terms of coordinates as long as we
express them in terms of combinations of
things which are themselves invariant.
All right, so we have four vectors.
Let's just label the general for vector
A.
It has four components.
And I'm going to label those four
components. A mu.
Mu is a Greek letter.
It looks like an M. It is an M. It's
Greek M.
And I'm going to put the index up on
top.
Right? For example,
the simplest for vector would be the
coordinates X mu. And what do they stand
for? They stand for four things. They
stand in particular for dt,
dx, dy, and dz.
I hear something's ringing. Is that in
my head?
That wasn't in my head.
We all heard it. Okay. All right. So, dx
mu just stands for the quadruple of
components of the four vector. Mu can be
thought of as going over four distinct
values and it's usually taken to go from
zero to three. DT is usually considered
the zeroth component of the vector 1 2
3. That's completely uh arbitrary. The
fact that the time component of a vector
is considered its zeroth component
rather than its fourth component.
Right? So this is the same as dx0
dot dot dot dot dot. Same thing.
Now
we multiply these things together to
form invariance. But we multiply them
together with a funny sign. All right,
the funny sign distinguishing d the the
dt^ 2 from the dx squ d y^2 and dz^ 2.
There's a notation for that. I think the
notation I'm not sure who invented the
notation. Uh
somebody uh probably in the 19th century
it might have been Reman. It might have
been Levy Chivder. I'm not sure who it
was, but one of the early differential
geometries, I don't think it was
Einstein, but I'm not sure. No, I don't
think so. Uh, invented the following
notation. Supposing I invent a new
object, not dt, dx, dy, dz, but a new
object which is exactly the same set of
co components,
except I change the sign of the time
component, dx, dy, dz.
All it is is the same object except with
the time component having its sign
changed.
Then the notation for that is dx with a
subscript like that.
It's the same object except its time
component has been changed. Every time
you take a vector and you change the
time component by a sign, it either
corresponds to raising or lowering the
index. If I have the lower index object,
here it is right here, and I change the
sign of the time component, it becomes
the upper indexed object. If I take the
upper indexed object and change the sign
of the time component, it becomes the
lower indexed object. All right? So,
this is purely notation. There's no
physics in it. It's purely notation for
another object. But now I can rewrite
that invariant. This ds^2 that's all da
squared the proper time squared.
Instead of writing it dt ^2us dx^ 2 - d
y^2 - dz^ 2 which I get rather tired of
doing. I write it in the form dx mu dx
with a lower mu.
Now again notations.
This was Einstein who realized he was
writing down too many summation signs.
He realized after a while that all of
his summation signs in his various
equations were always summations over
things with upper indices and lower
indices next to each other.
So he got the bright idea was one of the
brilliant extrapolations of physics that
whenever you see a thing with an upper
and a lower index next to each other
automatically sum over them
automatically. Don't even ask the
question whether you sum you do sum. dx
super mu sub mu
is by definition the sum over the four
components. Let's see what it says. dx
mu mu. Let's start with the first
component the north component. the time
component that's just equal to dt for
the upper component guy and then for the
lower component guy it's another dt but
with a minus sign
minus dt ^2 in other words
then there's the upper component dx and
the lower component dx they're both dx x
you don't we haven't changed any sign so
that's plus dx^2
and likewise for y and z
so this object is just shorthand for
minus dt ^2 do I really want minus I um
yeah I do
no it's fine it's it's the way I want it
this is shorthand the x super mu dx
submu is shorthand And for the not the
sums of squares but the difference of
squares where time components always
come in with an extra minus sign.
Now
here's something interesting. This
object is invariant.
Therefore this object is invariant.
This generalizes.
If we generalize, if we have a for
vector which transforms the same way as
dx mu,
then we label dx super mu the xyz and t.
If it transforms the same way as those
things, then we label it with an upper
index just like dx mu is labeled here.
That stands for the four components. I
won't bother writing them. the four
components, the four components of the
vector.
But we can also invent a symbol with a
lower index. The only difference is the
time components of these two have the
opposite sign. The space components have
the same sign.
If we construct the analog of what's
written here, namely a mu
a mu that's the time component squared
minus the space component squared. That
quantity is invariant
doesn't change under Lorent
transformation. So, we're beginning to
build up a calculus or a set of rules
for forming invariance.
And the rules are keep track of your
indices, sum over repeated indices, and
make sure that an upper one always
accompanies a lower one. That will build
up invariance made up out of pairs of
vectors. Now, it's a little more general
than this. I haven't told you the story
in full generality.
Here's an exercise for you to prove.
Supposing you have two vectors,
not two-dimensional vectors, but a pair
of four vectors,
a mu
and b mu,
a pair of them. Both of them transform
the same way as the components x, y, and
z and t. All right? Then you can make an
object
a super mu b sub mu.
Again, that's intended. Let's write down
what that means.
It means
the time component of A times the time
component. Well, let's
yeah, let's let's write. It means the
time component of A
times the time component of B, but with
a minus sign because when you lower an
index, that means a minus sign. And then
plus the x component
times the x component of b plus likewise
for the y component
plus a z bz b yeah it's the analog of
the dotproduct
between two vectors except with a minus
sign for the time components. The analog
of the dotproduct. In fact, this piece
over here is just the dotproduct between
the spatial pieces of the vector. The
time pieces come in with the opposite
sign. And that you can see because one
of these has a lower index, the other
has an upper index. And so the the
relative sign of the time components is
opposite. In fact, there's no difference
between this and putting the lower index
here and the upper index here. It
doesn't matter which of the two vectors
you flip the sign of the time component.
The product of them will come in with a
minus sign. So both of these objects
here are invariance.
They're like the dotproduct between two
vectors and the dotproduct between two
vectors is something which doesn't
doesn't change under rotation.
The Loren variant dotproduct it's not
called a dotproduct the inner product
the Loren variant inner product of two
vectors is also something which will not
change when you do Lorren transformation
now this is something to check this is
something you can check take any two
four vectors transform them to a new
coordinate system and then check that a
mu b mu doesn't change that it has the
same value before and after the
transformation information. So, as I
said, we're beginning to build up a
vocabulary for forming invariant
quantities.
Yeah,
we can transform that to polar form.
Say it again.
We can transform to spherical
coordinates.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no. Not sp
No, no. We're doing um uh coordinate
transformations between inertial
reference frames.
Okay, inertial reference frames means
cartisian coordinates and uniform
velocity.
Okay, we can rotate coordinates and
transform along some other axis, but
we're not talking about things like
polar coordinates at the moment.
Inertial reference frames all refer to
just the relationship between two
frames.
Yeah. Well, okay. So um
first of all an inertial reference frame
means the spatial coordinates are
cartisian coordinates.
Okay conventional cartisian coordinates
uh
just x y and z with the usual rules for
manipulating cartisian coordinates and
it means that the two coordinate frames
are in mo constant motion relative to
each other. That's the relationship
between two inertial frames. One more
statement.
An inertial frame, a single one. If we
had one single inertial frame, then we'd
be able to define an infinite number of
them by transforming from one to
another. All right? So, you have to
start with one inertial frame. One
inertial frame means a frame where
Newton's laws are satisfied or where
Einstein's generalization of Newton's
laws are satisfied. In other words, F
equals MA. Okay? So that's all that goes
into the idea of an inertial frame that
there's one inertial frame some out
there where Newton's laws are satisfied
and any other which is related by Lorent
transformation is is also an inertial
frame.
Okay. So that's the idea of building up
invariance out of four vectors.
As I said an even more primitive and
simple concept uh is the invariant
itself.
uh there are invariants which are not
built up out of four vectors. They just
happen to be invariants. I mean what's
another example? The trouble is to find
examples in relativity theory you have
to know a little more physics than uh
than that. But if we were just talking
about rotation of coordinates and not
Lorent transformation there would be
things which are scalers which would be
very familiar.
Uh temperature is a scalar. It doesn't
matter if you hold your thermometer this
way, that way, that way, this way, or
that way.
In other words, it doesn't matter what
axes you orient your thermometer along,
you get the same temperature.
Pressure, air pressure is also a uh a
scalar, an invariant. Uh that's a little
bit less obvious that if you had a
pressure meter, you make a How do you
make a pressure meter? Oh, I don't know.
You make a pressure meter. Uh, it's not
obvious that the pressure meter, Here's
my pressure meter. It's not obvious that
if I turn the pressure meter upside
down, I get the same pressure. Why?
Well, is all the air resting on it from
above. You might think that it uh that
it would squeeze it down more
if you hold a pressure meter this way
than if you hold it that way. Well, it's
not true. The air is pressing as much
from underneath as it is from here. Air
pressure is a scaler. It doesn't matter
which way you hold it. What What is a
What is a pressure meter called?
Monometer
is not
Is that a barometer?
Well, that be
he said.
What's a barometer?
Barometer is a column of fluid.
Doesn't that measure air pressure?
Gravity.
Hm. Under gravity. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
That's right. That's the
burden gauge does.
Yeah. Yeah.
You know, burn gauge is a piece of metal
that's got air inside it and it winds or
unwinds.
Yeah. There's there's many ways to make
a pressure meter. You might just take a
uh a cell, put a rubber membrane over
it, seal a rubber membrane, and then
when you put a lot of pressure on it,
the rubber membrane goes this way. If
you take off the pressure, the rubber,
you know, all kinds of ways of making
Don't you need to distinguish between
the actual quantity and the way you
measure it. I mean, the quantity itself
may be fixed, but the way you measure it
may depend upon certain physical
properties.
Well, you know, sometimes sometimes the
only really good definitions of
quantities are through how you measure
them. In fact, I think that's more or
less always the case. But uh but I I get
the point.
When you say it's invariant, you mean
you get the same pressure of a moving
frame?
No.
No, it's invariant under rotations, not
under lent transformations,
right? Only under rotations.
So with respect to the rotations,
pressure, temperature are invariants. Uh
what's a weather quantity which is not
an invariant?
Wind velocity. Wind velocity is what?
It's a vector. It's got a magnitude and
it's got a direction and its components
do depend on your orientation. The x
component will change if you change what
you call the x-axis.
So its components are the components of
a vector.
Another good scale are humidity.
Humidity is a good but so is wind speed.
Wind speed. What does speed mean? Speed
is the magnitude of the velocity.
Speed is not velocity because by
definition it's the the the term speed
officially means the magnitude of
velocity.
In fact, the speed is just the square
root of the sums of the squares of the
components of the wind velocity. So the
wind speed is an invariant and therefore
kind of qualifies as a scalar for me.
The wind velocity which has a sense of
direction is not a scalar. All right. So
we now know what we mean by vectors.
Four vectors scalers and we know how to
make some scalers out of four vectors.
If we go back to the problem of
uh well okay that's it's
now there's another quantity another
class of quantities which are
interesting which also have four
components.
They are also four vectors
a little bit different. Oh, before I say
that, let me uh let me just say one
thing. If I have a known for vector,
let's call it a and I have another set
of objects b mu which I'm not sure
whether they're a for vector or not.
I'm not sure whether they transform as a
four vector. There's a test you
calculate in every frame of reference
the inner product. And if the inner
product doesn't change, if the inner
product is a scalar,
if the inner product of two objects, one
of which is known to be a four vector
and the other you're testing,
if that inner product doesn't change
from frame to frame, in other words,
supposing somebody gave you a four
vector, they told you it was a four
vector, and then they gave you another
set of four quantities. They gave it to
you in every frame of reference, but
they didn't tell you whether it was a
four vector or not. Then you compute the
inner product a mu b mu. And if it's the
same in every reference frame, then b mu
is a four vector. That's a theorem. It's
a simple elementary theorem that if you
have one for vector and you're testing
another one, if the inner product is
invariant, then the result is a then b
must be a four vector. Okay, let's move
on to another object.
the derivative. Supposing I have a
scalar quantity such as the temperature
in three dimensions or some other field.
Now we come to the idea of a field. A
field in space. A field in space there
are many different kinds of fields. Some
fields are vector fields. For example,
well uh if we're just talking about
three dimensions, wind velocity is a
field. Of course, it's not a field in
the sense of a fundamental field of any
kind, but it is a field. It varies from
place to place. It can have equations
which govern it. It's a vector field,
right? Not a four vector field, a three
vector field. All right? As we said,
temperature, humidity are scalers.
Imagine now that we have a scalar with
respect to the Lorent transformations
that let's call it fi. Fi is Greek F and
F stands for field. It's a field. It
depends on position in general. X, Y, Z,
and T, let's just call it F ofX, where X
stands for all four components.
If it's a scalar field, it means that
everybody who measures it, no matter how
they're moving relative to each other,
no matter what their orientation of
their axes, they will agree about the
value of it.
Now, do anybody know some examples of
four uh fourdimensional fields which are
uh which are scalers? You probably don't
because they're not familiar, but
nevertheless, do you know any
fields in spaceime fundamental fields
which happened to uh uh to be
electrostatic field? No, the
electrostatic field is is the compon is
not a four vector. It has three
components. First of all, so it can't be
a scalar.
In fact, it can't even be a four vector.
It's only got three components. The
magnetic fields,
the Higs field, the Higs field, right?
The Higs field is the first real
fundamental scalar field that occurs in
physics.
Why the Higsfield is so unfamiliar to
you? Well, that's an experimental
physics question. Why is the Higsfield
uh the way it is? Uh it's an
experimental physics question,
theoretical physics question. But the
Higsfield is a scalar field simply means
that uh that it doesn't depend its value
doesn't depend on how you're moving
relative to it or how you're oriented
relative to it.
Vloit
good. The magnitude of any four. Yeah.
Yeah. Good. Take any four vector field
and take its magnitude.
Good. That's one. Uh do you know any
four vector field?
The four velocity. No, no, for um
I don't usually think of that as a
field, but by field I meant a thing like
a gravitational field or uh
you want any uh
we we were we it took us a while to find
a scalar. Somebody said Higs. How about
a four vector?
Well, the uh the
potential and the vector potential for
vector. Yeah, the electromagnetic fay
field is built out of a four vector,
namely the components of the
fourdimensional vector potential.
All right. Uh it's a little bit tricky
what its transformation properties are,
but let's let's make it simple. The
square of the uh or not strictly not the
square but the square in this sense a mu
a mu this could be the four vector
vector potential. This combination then
of the four vector potential with
itself.
The time component squared minus the
space component squared would also be a
scalar.
About energy and momentum.
Uh no. Well, first of all, energy and
momentum are not fields. They are
quantities that describe a whole system.
All right? But there are flows of
energy. Energy density, momentum
density, and that sort of thing. Energy
density is not a four vector is not is
not a scalar. It's a three-dimensional
scaler. It doesn't change when you
rotate, but it does change when the
system is moving relative to you. All
right? You take a system with a given
energy. And now you look at it from a
frame of reference where you're moving
very fast. It has a lot more energy. So
energy and momentum form a for vector.
Not a not a scalar.
things like the Hamiltonian. Is that it?
No, that's the energy. That's energy.
That's energy, right? So, it's a four
it's a component of a four vector.
It's a four vector together with the
momentum of a system. The energy and
momentum of a system form a four vector.
Well, we we'll have to come back to
that. We'll have to come back to that
because it's important. Uh
but energy and momentum come together.
Energy being the time component,
momentum being the space component. So
it's not that there aren't that many
around that are familiar. What about the
gravitational field?
Gravitational field is not a scalar.
It's not even a for vector. It's a
tensor of some kind. We're going to come
to tensors. It just means it has more
indices, but we'll come to that uh
later. So
it's not so easy to find examples
uh of relativistic scalers and for
vectors and so forth that you're
familiar with. But the concept is easy.
Just a field fi which no matter how
you're oriented relative to it, no
matter how you're moving relative to it,
always has the same value when measured.
Okay, that's called a scalar. Now you
can differentiate scalers. You can
differentiate them. You can take their
partial derivatives with respect to
different directions. For example, you
can take the partial derivative
of phi with respect to time.
Let's call that
fi subt.
Well, that's not quite right. five,
comma t
ah five t. Just leave it 5t like that.
That stands for the derivative of phi
with respect to t. We could also
indicate it by a dot on top, but I want
to indicate it this way. The derivative
of phi with respect to time.
That's one component of something that
has some more components. The derivative
of phi with respect to x.
Let's just call that fi subx.
It's not the this I'm afraid I might uh
confuse notation. This is not the t
component of phi.
It's the t component of a vector made
out of the derivatives of phi. There are
four such derivatives. Derivative of phi
with respect to t. Derivative of ph with
respect to x. Likewise z. And likewise
y. I guess I missed the four derivatives
of phi can be grouped together and
called partial of phi with respect to x
mu.
Notice we have a mu index now or with
this simplified notation. I only
introduce it to save myself from writing
uh too many things. Just call it phi sub
mu.
The derivative of phi with respect to x
mu. This is a complex of four objects
which contain a time component and four
and three space components.
It's pretty obvious. Well, at least it
should be sort of psychologically
obvious uh that uh psychologically
meaning to say if I'm if I introduce it
and I give it an index like that, it's
pretty clear that it's some sort of four
vector has four components. looks like a
duck, acts like a duck. It's a it's it's
a four vector. It is a four vector. The
only question is whether it should be
thought of as a four vector with an
upper component or a lower component.
Incidentally, the things with upper
components and lower components
transform slightly differently.
There are some funny minus signs when
you transform the vectors with the lower
index. In fact, if you take the Laurent
transformation and every time you see a
time component change the sign of it,
you get the transformation properties of
the object with the lower index. So
lower index objects transform slightly
different than upper index objects. They
are different and they differ only in
the sign of the time component.
Should we identify d5 by dx mu as a
thing with an upper index or a lower
index?
Okay, that's an interesting question.
The answer is with a lower index
consistent with what I've written here.
But how do we prove that? How do we
prove that
uh
that d5 by dx mu
is a for vector of the lower kind?
Incidentally, what's the name for uh for
things with upper indices and lower
indices? Anybody remember
covariant and contravariant. The ones
with the upper indices are called
contravariant
coariant. Coarant
coariant and the ones with lower indices
are called contravariant.
Co is low
coariant low.
Co is low.
Well, then everybody had it backwards. I
never remember. I can't remember. I'm uh
I just call them the upper guys and the
lower guys.
And uh
the derivatives
have
the same kind of coordinates as
I would have called them covariant.
Yeah, I would call this coariant but I
may have it backward.
and dx mu I would call contravariant but
I may again I may have it backward
h
I think I'm right yeah
okay let's try to prove that the 5y by
dx mu is a covariant are the covariant
components of a four vector now here's
what we need to do we if we can find
some known for vector vector
and we combine it together with the
thing which we're testing
and what we get out is a scalar then
we're assured that the thing that we're
testing is a four vector. In particular,
if we take a known thing which
corresponds to a contravariant,
yeah, contravariant for a vector and we
combine it together with something which
we suspect is a covariant for a vector
and we always get a scalar. We always
get the same thing out, then we're
assured that the thing with the lower
index here really does transform in the
right way.
All right, we have something. Yeah,
naive kind of question about your
notation there.
Say it again.
Uh, naive kind of question.
Naive question.
Yeah, the the x has a mu upper.
Yeah,
but the f has a mu lower.
This just means derivative with respect
to x mu.
He's troubled because x is x.
Oh, you're troubled because this one is
upstairs and this one's downstairs.
Yeah. Yeah, I know. But the dx the
derivative with respect to dx is down
below the fraction bar. Doesn't that
convince you?
It shouldn't. The only thing that should
convince you is a proper test.
So, let's do the proper test. I think
the the
image that
I heard supposed to work is that is the
tangent
coaries with the surface. Do it like
and that's why you have the derivatives
as
well I don't get it but let's let's do
the test.
The test is to find some known covariant
for vector with a upper index
multiply it together with this thing sum
over mu and check whether the result is
the same in every reference frame.
Anybody got a suggestion for a known uh
yeah here's here's the test. Take two
points two neighboring points.
Phi is of course a field. It varies from
point to point,
right?
It varies from point to point. But it's
important to realize that the sum of
scalers is another scalar. The
difference of scalers is a scalar.
All right? So let's let's take these two
points which are separated by a small
distance dx mu.
dx mu are the components of the
coordinates the coordinate components of
the displacement between the two points.
Now this is a known for vector. It's a
known contravariant for vector that
transforms as a coariant as a for
vector. Let's multiply it
by
dy by dx mu
dx
and sum over mu. What? Anybody know what
this quantity is?
It's partial derivative of five with
respect to t * dt plus partial of
derivative of ph with respect to x dx
plus partial of derivative of five with
respect to y dy.
It's just the difference of phi at the
two end points.
Let's call this end point two. Let's
call this endpoint one.
You could call it just defi. It's the
difference
of phi.
phi at 2 minus fi at 1.
It's the change in phi when you move in
one direction times the change in x
etc etc. It just gives you the small
change in phi when you move from one
point to another.
Phi is a scalar. Differences of scalers
are scalers.
So the right hand side is a scalar.
The left hand side is the product of a
known contravariant vector with
something that we're testing.
We've successfully tested that defy by
dx mu is a four vector of the covariant
kind of the kind with the lower index
and that's because it does not change
equal z
right so now we found some more
interesting objects
derivatives of fields
We have covariant sorry contravariant
vectors dx mu.
We have covariant vectors dy by dx mu.
We can turn a co a contravariant vector
into a covariant vector by changing the
the sign of its time component. So
we can invent the covariant version of a
particular contravariant vector
in like manner. This of course is fi sub
mu. In like manner we can invent a
contravariant version of this derivative
here. How? just by changing the sign of
the time component in which case it
becomes fi super mu with a superscript.
The only difference is
both of these fi's are made up out of
derivatives of phi with respect to time
and space.
But the time component of this is minus
the derivative of phi with respect to
time. So this complex here stands for dy
by dt
dy by dx and the others. This one stands
for minus d5 by dt
and d5 by dx.
What happens if we take we multiply this
one by this one? In other words, what
happens if we take phi with a super mu
and multiply it by phi with a sub mu and
sum over mu?
What does that give? Well, it gives us
derivative of five with respect to t ^2
with a minus sign
and then plus signs the square of d5 by
dx and the square of d5 by dy and the
square of d5 by dz. Is that an
invariant?
Yes, it's an invariant because it's
composed out of an upper index and a
lower index and that's our rule.
So for example, we've now discovered a
new scalar. The new scalar is minus dy
by dt^ 2
+ d5 by dx^ 2
plus d5 by d y^ 2
plus d5 by dz ^ 2.
Any observer in any inertial reference
frame, any Lorren frame who measures in
his own reference frame the components
of the derivatives of phi with respect
to time, with respect to space and
combine, those derivatives will not
agree in different frames of reference.
They're components of a vector. But if
we take the combination minus d5 by dt ^
2 plus d5 by dx^ 2 d y^2 d5 dz ^ 2 that
quantity is the same in every reference
frame and is a scalar. So we have a
scala
and
in shorthand notation it's just d mui
d super mui.
So again I emphasize what we're
generating is a kind of calculus of
invariance ways of building invariance
out of vectors derivatives
differentials
for vectors of various kinds. All right,
let's take a little break and then we'll
come back
to the
waves moving on a screen but in light of
what we've learned up till now.
All right. So, let me write down on the
blackboard
the scaler that we've discovered.
take a scaler and begin with a scalar
and construct it the components of its
derivatives.
In other words, we could call it its
gradient uh for vector d5 by dx mu.
So many ways to write it. All right, we
could write it this way.
We could write it this way. They all
mean the same thing. and we could write
it just fi mu
all mean the same thing.
Okay, we can also construct a
contravariant version of this. As was
pointed out by somebody here,
uh strictly speaking, when you construct
a contravariant
vector, you're talking about a thing in
a different space, the dual space. But
let's not worry about that. That's a uh
a fine point of mathematics, which is
important and interesting, but uh we
don't need to
be so technical at this point. You just
change the sign of the time component.
And I'm not going to try to write this
one. We can write d super muupi.
So you could just lower the right.
Yeah, I could put it down here, couldn't
I?
A lower thing in the denominator means
an upper thing.
the super mui or fi super mu
all mean the same thing. These two sets
of objects are the same objects with a
time component having the opposite sign.
And then we discovered that the
combination
d mufi
is also a scalar
and in fact what is it? It's dti^
squar minus dxi^ 2ar
minus d y5^ 2. All right, I'll write it.
I never really understood why neat
notations were invented until I started
teaching.
You get really sick of writing things
like this. Here it is. D sub mu d super
mu the other way.
Oh, thank you. Minus signs the other
way.
Incidentally, the scalers no matter
which way with either way. They're a
scalar, but with a minus sign here, it
corresponds to the definitions that I've
already used.
You could just use eyes for the other
one.
I
for the space
you use I for the spacing and for the
Oh, you could. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. Or not for the fourth index and I
for that. Yeah. Now do keep in mind I've
left out some some uh speeds of light.
I've set the speed of light equal to
one. There are some places you can
restore the speeds of light uh just by
dimensional analysis.
I won't do it here and now.
Okay. Let's come back to the problem
that we addressed last time of a string
vibrating
in the plane perpendicular
to the orientation of the length of the
violin.
We define the vertical coordinate of the
string by calling it phi.
String is vibrating the vertical
coordinate of any point. Remember the
string was made up of a bunch of points.
We took a limit in which the points
became denser and denser and basically
fi sub i which was the height. I does
not stand for direction of space. It
stands for the i particle along the
chain.
Fi being the vertical direction. x being
the horizontal direction. Phi being the
vertical direction. fi morphed into a
field
which just became fi of x. fi of x was
the displacement in the vertical
direction of the field. Incidentally, we
may uh we will either I was I hope to do
it today. I don't think I'll get to it.
I was going to study uh strings which
vibrate both vertically and
horizontally. There's an interesting
point there. But uh
uh we could also do strings which
vibrate along their own direction, but
I'm not going to do that tonight. All
right. So this fi fi sub i meaning the
five coordinate of the i particle became
fi of x.
We also wrote down
an action principle. Let me just remind
you quickly what that action principle
was. It contained in a discrete form
before we took the limit. It contained
kinetic terms and potential terms. The
kinetic terms. Now I'm going to use sum
because I'm not summing over indices.
I'm summing over particles.
Sum over all the particles
5 I do 2 / 2. And then there was a mass
for each particle which I took to be
epsilon or proportional to epsilon.
epsilon
was the
x separation between neighboring uh
between neighboring
points on the string
or neighboring neighboring sites and
then there was another term this was the
lranian I'm writing down this was the
kinetic energy and then minus the
potential energy and the potential
energy had a spring constant which was 1
over epsilon I think I put a c^ squ
Yeah.
Uh later on we're going to set C to one
again. And then I think it was 5 I - 5 I
+ 1 squared.
Okay. Everybody remember that? Anybody?
Oh, it is a two.
All right. Spring constant went like one
over epsilon. Mass went like epsilon.
And we played with it. We worked out the
equations of motion.
Took the continuum limit. The continuum
limit is the limit in which epsilon
shrinks to zero and in which we replace
the discrete variable fi i by f ofx.
And let me remind you in particular what
happened to the lranjian. Oh, there was
the lranjian and there was the action.
Here's the lranjian
and the action
is the integral dt
from some initial starting point to some
end point of the lrangeian itself.
Well, when we took the limit in which we
let the epsilon shrink to zero,
something nice happened.
Let's recall what it was.
We did it two ways.
One way we did it was to write the
equation of motion itself
and then take the limit in the equation
of motion. What we got was the wave
equation. Let me write down the wave
equation. It was
d2 by dt ^2. That of course is just the
acceleration
of a point on the string. the vertical
acceleration of a point on the string
the second derivative with respect to
time and that was equal is it uh yeah uh
c^2
let's just write it minus c ^2 second
derivative of phi with respect to x^2
that was not exactly what we had what we
had was
let me remind you what we had was
well we had some discrete form of the
second derivative. I'm not going to
repeat it. Go back to your notes.
We worked out the equation of motion and
then took the limit that epsilon went to
zero replacing differences by
derivatives.
There was a sec there was a der a
difference of a difference which became
a second derivative. Everybody remember
that?
Good. Okay. Now we could have done the
same operation
by figuring out what happens to the
lrangeian the same limit and we did so
we actually did so we found out that
this term here the first term first of
all the sum became an integral
dx
the phi dot squared well that's just
derivative of phi with respect to uh t
^2
is still there
and then minus
I'm going to set C equal to one.
Now
C in the original problem had nothing to
do with the speed of light. It had to do
with the speed of propagation up and
down a violin string. Of course,
secretly we all knew that eventually I
was going to say it was the speed of
light. Not because violin strings move
with the speed of light, but because
this was just a model for a uh
relativistic field. All right. So, let's
set C equal to one. And this term became
minus D5 by DX^2
integral DX
that is the Lrangeian, but it's not the
action. The action is you take the
lrangeian and integrate it over time.
The act the lrangeian itself is an
integral over space. What it's doing is
it's adding up all the points along the
string. That's what this x integration
is doing here. Adding up all the points.
Let me let me move the x d the x to the
back here.
All right. So dx integration adds up all
the points along the string.
It's a standin for the sum over i. But
the integral dt that converts the
lranian into an action. The thing
which goes into the principle of least
action. All we have to do is write dt
here.
Did I hear a question?
No question.
He wants you. He wants another integral
sign, I guess. No, no, no. One integral
sign is enough.
The number of integrations is told to
you by how many D's ds you have?
Okay. You really want me to write
another integral?
No.
No. All right. So, it's an integral over
space and time.
In the problem that we set up, space
extended over some finite interval from
the peg to the bridge.
So space was some finite integral inter
interval.
And in the principle of least action, we
also introduce an interval in time. The
time from the start to the end of the
process. We introduce initial conditions
at the beginning, final conditions at
the end and we ask what is the history
of the system which interpolates between
the initial state and the final state
and which minimizes the action. So
there's also an initial time and a final
time
and the action becomes an integral
of a certain quantity which involves the
field and its derivatives. integrated
over this region.
This is not supposed to represent the
string. It's just supposed to color in
the region where you do the integral.
Well, by now, of course, you've made the
connection that at least for this
one-dimensional problem, what goes here
is exactly the scalar.
Of course, that's only true if we take
uh the C to be the speed of light.
But
this has exactly the same form as the
scalar. I've eliminated two d two
dimensions. Y and z don't play any role
in all of this. We're only talking about
motion of waves up and down a particular
axis. Now the x- axis. Uh
and it's no accident. It's not an
accident that the lrangeian here
takes this form of a quantity which
appears to be lorenvariant which appears
to be a scala.
What this tells us?
Well, what do you think it tells us
about uh about the equations which
follow from this lrangeian?
Here's here's the principle. The
principle is minimize the action
with the action being defined by this
integral over space and time of a
certain scalar.
Equations of motion will be loren.
The equations of motion are loren.
Start with the scalerian
wind up with a lens.
That's right.
Equations of motion.
That's right. If you start with a scaler
for the lrangeian the lrangeian then
this. Okay. Let's let's get some
terminology right now. Script L by the
time we went this far. Well, no, no.
Script L is the lrangeian. Let's let's
call it capital L.
But capital L itself
is an integral over space. The lrangeian
is an integral over space. Let's get all
the things down. Yeah, let me write them
down in one place over here. Uh
the lrangeian
began as a sum over i. It morphed into
an integral dx.
The thing that went into the integral,
the integrant
I can call script l.
What is it composed out of? It's
composed out of the derivatives.
It's a function of the derivatives
of phi with respect to the various
coordinates. It could also involve fi. I
mean this is not the most general thing
we can write down. This is what we got
by hooking springs together with uh
violin strings. This is called the
lrangege density. It's called lrangee
density because you integrate it over
space to find the full lrangeian.
But then you go to the action. The
action is the integral of L over time.
And that becomes
the integral over X and T
of the same quantity of the same Lrange
density. I won't bother writing down
what it depends on. So you can almost
think that the Lrange density is a kind
of action density. In fact, that's what
it is. It's the action per unit
space-time volume per dxdt.
That's what this lrangege density is.
You can think of it as a thing that you
integrate over space to find the
lrangeian. And so it's the lrangee
density. But it's also the thing that
you integrate over space and time to
find the action. So it can properly be
called the action density. But the
action density in spacetime, not the
action density in space, but the action
density in spaceime.
All right. Now, uh
that mean
the lrange density is a scalar.
Well, let's put it this way. If the
lrangee density is a scalar, then the
equations are invariant under Loren
transformation.
All right, that's the criteria for an
action which will give Loren variant
equations that the action itself be
invariant and that entails the integrant
being a scala.
So if the integrant is a scala the
equations of a theory will be Lorren
invariant.
I've left out some details
uh and even some logically important
details but I think we've captured the
essence of the idea of uh invariance
and how you build invariant laws of
nature from invariant action principles.
Okay. Um
let's go a little bit f far f far f far
f far f far f far f far f far f far f
far f far further.
Supposing we actually wanted to
construct a field that uh vibrated
around not along an axis along a violin
string but uh that moved throughout all
of space and time xyz and t. The
strategy is quite clear. All we have to
do in order to find the loren variant
description in fourdimensional space
this is in two-dimensional space one
time in one space. All we have to do is
fill out the rest of this expression and
write
the action
equals 12 the integral. Now this becomes
a fourdimensional integral not a
two-dimensional integral. A
fourdimensional integral I could write
the x dy dz dt but I can also just write
d4x.
That's the standard symbol for
integrating dx dy dz dt d4x
and it means an integral over volume
elements in spacetime not in space but
in spacetime and then
d mui
d mui now I have something wrong here
what I have wrong here is that the
kinetic energy comes in with a plus sign
Here I've written it in such a way that
it has a minus sign. So normally you
would put a minus there.
All right, with the minus there, it's
just equal to integral
let's call it 5 t^2 - 5x^2
- 5 y^ 2 - 5 z ^2
where you know what I mean by 5 subt and
5 subx y and z just the derivatives
right
this is a sca this is a scalar
the action itself is invariant the same
in every reference frame and therefore
the problem that you set up when you say
let me find what minimizes the action
doesn't really depend on the frame of
reference.
Now let's talk about let's see how far
how much more time do we have? We have a
little more time.
You know I think I'm going to stop here.
I think we've done enough for tonight uh
and take some questions. What I wanted
to talk about was given a lrange density
given a script L how do you generate the
equations of motion in a simple way.
The overall strategy is clear minimize
the action but how do you convert that
to differential equations? How do you
convert that to wave equations? And
we'll talk about that next time. But
I'll just remind you very quickly that
the same question occurs when thinking
about particle mechanics.
We had an action which depended on the
trajectory of a particle.
We wanted to minimize that action. That
sounds like a global problem that
involves the whole trajectory. But we
converted it to a differential equation
which only involved the first and second
derivatives of the motion. And we did it
by focusing on a little piece over here
and saying if we've actually minimized
the action then we must have also
minimized the action between these two
points if everything else is kept fixed.
And so we just take these two points and
we explore around what trajectory
between these two points minimizes the
action between the neighboring points.
And that's what gave us a local
differential equation. We could either
concentrate on the global issue or we
could concentrate on it locally,
minimize the action between two nearby
points and that gives the local
differential equations. We're going to
do exactly the same thing next time.
I'll probably just write down the
answer. But uh but let me tell you what
the strategy is. We have some space-time
region
and we want to minimize the action. We
want to know what field configuration.
In other words, what history of the
field? What does a history mean? In the
case of the violin string, it means a
history of all the points on the string.
An entire motion of the string from
beginning to end. In the case of a
general field, it means the entire
motion of that field in space and time.
What motion of the field in space and
time minimizes
the action?
Right? We could try to solve that by
exploring all possible functions that
can fit in this space-time box. But we
could also do it another way. We could
say supposing we know the value of the
field on some little boundary here. All
right. What if we know the value of the
field? If somebody somebody told us that
the solution of the problem involves the
field having a certain value on a little
region on on the boundary of a little
region and asked us to figure out what
it was doing inside, we would say all we
have to do is minimize the action in
that little region there subject to the
constraint that it has some fixed value
on the boundary. that gives us
differential equations. In the same way
that focusing on a little piece of the
trajectory
took us from the action principle
basically to F= ma
doing the same thing taking a little
region
and requiring that the action be minimal
within that little region takes us from
this grand action principle to the local
differential wave equations. Where are
we? Did we do we I think we erased the
wave equation. In fact, I don't even
think we ever wrote it down.
Well, I'll write it down next time.
Well, actually, you abbreviated it
pretty much like that.
Well, here's the action.
Well,
let me remind you what the wave equation
was. I think I did write it down. Yeah,
it was second derivative of PH with
respect to t^2
minus second derivative of ph with
respect to x^2 is equal to zero.
So we either could think of that as the
equation coming from this discrete
problem of a bunch of points connected
by springs or we can think about it in a
more space-timeyy kind of way and say
it's the equation that comes by
minimizing the action over some tiny
little patch of spaceime given that uh
we had already figured out what was
going on on the boundary of that region
and that defines for us the the wave
equation. So it's back and forth between
grand global
principles which have the advantage that
they tell us manifestly that the theory
doesn't depend on the particular Lorren
frame on the one hand and going back and
forth to differential equations which
are of course in general easier to uh uh
they're the things you want to write
down and solve
using uh differential equation theory.
Okay, I think we're about finished for
tonight and next time we'll get into the
business of actually writing down field
equations and solving them from various
action principles like this. Yeah.
Isn't the wave equation that you wrote
down just
density setal?
No, no, no, no, no, no. These are second
derivatives. These are squares of first
derivatives.
Thank you.
Right. That was a perfect question to
ask because I meant to say it and I
forgot. Incidentally, can you think of
something else we might add into this
lrangeian here that would still keep it
invariant?
Yeah, any constant.
Well, any constant of course
any any velocity
we want what's in here to be a scalar.
Five is a scalar. We could add five in.
We could add five squared
5 cub 54 function of five. Any function
of five we could add in there
and we will do so. Okay.
Yeah.
Underneath the the board the the last
expression you wrote there the integral
uh should be also uh d4 x.
Yeah.
After that. Yeah. Yeah,
good.
Okay. D4X of course is just another
convenient notation
that saves me writing dtx dy dz
that has its own transformation property
I guess d4x
good that is a good point the question
is how does the differential quantity
itself transform and the answer is it's
a scala
right
the answer is that d4x is itself a scala
all right we'll come back to that.
That's a that's an important point. When
I when I said before I left out a little
piece of logic, it had to do with that.
It's a volume element.
It's not completely obvious that that uh
is a invariant, but it is.
Yeah. The model starts out with with the
spring constants with two constants, a
spring constants and the mass for a unit
string.
It ends up with just one constant C.
Yeah. Um, do you ever get to break C
into two parts? Mass and
Yeah. Okay. So, let's uh All right. So,
let's let's put back
the constants. Um, I always want there
to be an epsilon here and an epsilon
here because if those epsilons aren't
there, then it doesn't scale correctly
when you take the limit. But we could
put in another constant mu here. And we
have a constant there already. So, I
don't need another constant. So in
principle there could be two constants
there right who asked me a question
asked I just want to know are they
separately measurable or do you only
yeah they're separately measurable if we
know exactly what phi means if we really
know knew that fi meant height of this
thing in meters then we could measure it
yes but we can always take fi and absor
sorry mu and absorb it into phi
we could take we can invent a new
variable. Instead of fi,
let's call it I don't know what's
another Greek letter.
Alpha. No, I don't like alpha.
Nobody ever uses alpha for fields.
Kai. Kai. Good. Kai.
Kai. And let Kai equal the square root
of mu * fi.
All right. All I've done is taken the
square root of mu and grouped it with fi
with phi here. Then did I write what I
wanted to write? Yeah. Then ki squared
first of all is mu * 5^ 2
and the same is true of derivatives. K
dot squared
is mu * 5 dot 2. Right?
It's also true that I would have to
manipulate this over here. But by the
time I'm finished, I could eliminate the
constant out of here by redefining the
field with a square root of mu there.
All right. So I can redefine phi and
it'll be at the cost of changing the
constant over here.
Okay. When I write let's let's write it
this way. When I write that phi
is equal to ki over the square root of
mu and I do it everywhere as I do it
here I do it here it'll eliminate the mu
out of here
but it'll show up again over here
okay it'll show up in the denominator
over here but then I can just combine it
with c and say it was just a change of
the c that was here so really there's
only one constant that really enters
into the uh propagation of waves and
what it comes down to is the speed of
propagation.
That's all that's really left over in
the end after you make use of all the
freedom that you have in changing units.
It's basically a change of unit of the
uh of the of the fi axis.
So that's uh that's the answer to that
question. There's only one
think of it as a a mass instead of a
propagation speed.
Well, it's the propagation speed along a
uh string is composed out of two things.
It's composed out of the mass density
and the tension in the string.
All right? And those uh and basically
these are these two constants, but they
can be combined together into a single
variable.
Think of them as being the other way
around.
What's that?
Can you think of them as being the other
way around? you can roll the the your
uh speed of propagation kind of into the
mass of the system.
Yeah. Um
but you can all you can always rewrite
by changing the units of phi. You can
always rewrite it so that there's only
one constant and it's over here. You
could also rewrite it so the constant
over here was one. The constant shows up
over here.
But you have one constant that uh that
physically corresponds to the speed of
propagation and that's all for this wave
equation for this here. If you have
another con if you have another term for
example vi squared there could be a
numerical coefficient in front of that
and that would be new that would be new
stuff
that would be a new constant.
Yeah. um uh many semesters ago or terms
you when you started describing string
theory you started with the same model
of little springs and
yeah there's only so many different
things in physics that you can solve and
so
is there any significance that you
started with the same model or
that's yeah it's the only thing I know
heard
Well, is there a significance?
Not direct. Not direct.
Right.
Okay. Good. If there are no other
questions, let's uh and we're going to
go home and we're all going to make up
physics questions and put them on the uh
on the blog.
[Music]
The preceding program is copyrited by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.